Implementing a Thread Library on Linux (evanjones.ca)

[ 2003-December-10 11:12 ]

When a program is executed on a computer, it is executed a line at a time, which each line containing a command to execute, or directions about which piece of code to execute next. Sometimes, this is not sufficient. There are many programs which must be able to do many things at once. For example, a GUI application must repaint the display and respond to user input while doing any processing, and web servers must be able to send information to hundreds of clients simultaneously. This is the problem that threads try to solve. Threads allow multiple parts of a program to run at the same time. All modern operating systems supply some sort of thread library, such as standard Posix threads. However, I was curious about how threads actually work. So armed with a little bit of knowledge about C and the Linux kernel, I went out to build my own thread library.

在程序在運行的時候，通常都是只有一條主線的，有些時候，這是效率不高的。有很多程序必須要能同時做很多工作。比如說，GUI程序必須在處理程序邏輯的同時重畫界面，響應用戶輸入。Web服務器必須同時向成百上千的客戶發送信息。線程可以解決這些難題。所有的現代操作系統都提供線程庫，比如標準Posix線程。特別是，我對線程的工作原理十分好奇，所以在學習了一些C和Linux內核的知識後，我開始建立自己的線程庫。

Multitasking

In traditional operating systems, there are two tools for multitasking provided by the operating system. The first is a process, and the second is a thread.

在傳統的操作系統中，提供了實現多任務的兩種工具，一種是進程，一種是線程。

Processes

Each program is a seperate process. The operating system shares computing resources between all the processes that are running. It also keeps each process seperate, preventing one process from modifing another process's resources. However, it is quite common that many processes can belong to a single program. For example, the Figure 1 shows some of the processes currently running on my Linux system, and there are four processes executing mozilla-bin . In this case, one process will need to communicate with another. This is facilitated through operating system routines for inter-process communication (IPC), such as signals (signal ), shared memory (shmop ), and pipes (pipe ).

每個程序都是獨立的進程。操作系統在所有進程間分配資源，並且為了防止一個進程修改其他進程的資源，進程間是彼此完全獨立的。但是，多個進程配合完成一項任務也是很常見的。比如說，圖1展示了我的Linux系統下同時進行的進程，其中有4個進程執行mozilla-bin。在這種情況下，進程間需要相互通信，因此操作系統提供了進程間通信(IPC)的工具，比如有信號，共享內存和管道。

Process ID | Command
1 | init
142 | /sbin/syslogd
183 | /usr/bin/X11/X
266 | esd
270 | sawfish
275 | panel
277 | gmc
279 | gnome-terminal
291 | bash
319 | /usr/bin/mozilla-bin
341 | /usr/bin/scite
344 | /usr/bin/mozilla-bin
345 | /usr/bin/mozilla-bin
346 | /usr/bin/mozilla-bin
2568 | ps

Figure 1: Linux System Process List

Threads

Inter-process communication is simple and easy to use when it is used occasionally. However, if there are many processes and many resources to be shared between them, the model quickly becomes cumbersome. Threads were created to make this sort of resource sharing simple and efficient. The concept is that a single process can have a number of threads, and everything is shared between them except the execution context (the stack and CPU registers). This way, if a shared resource is modified in one thread, the change is visible in all other threads. The disadvantage is that care must be taken to avoid problems where two threads try to access a shared resource at the same time.

Kernel Threads

Modern operating systems directly support threads in the kernel, which means that the scheduling of which process is supposed to run is done by the operating system. Kernel threads allow the operating system to schedule different threads to run on different processors in multiprocessor computers, which can be an enormous performance increase. The disadvantage of kernel threads is that each time the operating system switches between threads, a context switch, there is a penalty due to the overhead of saving and restoring the state of the threads. Therefore, many simultaneous threads will be slower than a single thread which distributes its time between different tasks. This is the reason that single threaded web servers, like thttpd , perform better than multi-threaded web servers, like Apache . The JAWS research project has an excellent analysis of the performance of various multitasking approaches with respect to web servers.

User Space Threads

Threads can also be built in user space. This means that a library or program is responsable for scheduling and executing threads. When this is done in user space, there is still a penalty for a context switch. However, the cost is less than an operating system context switch. Sometimes, user space threads are called fibers, to suggest that they are "lighter" than kernel threads. For the remainder of this article, I will refer to user space threads as fibers, and kernel threads as threads. Fibers have an additional advantage over kernel threads: Only one thread can modify a shared resource at a time, since only one fiber can be executing at a time. This means that some of the locks required for threads may not be needed. However, care is still required. As mentioned in " Cooperative Task Management ", a 2002 USENIX paper, "Cooperative task management [user space threads] avoids the concurrency problems of locks only if tasks can complete without having to yield control to any other task." Fibers also cannot take advantage of multiprocessor systems. The author of GNU Pth, Ralf Engelschall, has an excellent paper about his work implementing user space threads , which covers the differences between different threading models in detail.

A Basic Thread Library

To play around with these concepts, a basic C thread library, libfiber , was written. It is implemented using two techniques for fibers and Linux kernel threads. This library provides an extremely simple implementation for creating, destroying and scheduling fibers or threads. It should only be used as an example for learning about how threads are implemented, since there are many issues with signals and synchronization. For real applications there are more polished libraries such as pthreads for kernel threads or GNU Portable Threads (Pth) for user space threads.

libfiber interface

void initFibers();
Initializes the internal structures inside the library. Should be called before using any library routines.
int spawnFiber( void (*func)(void) );
Creates a new thread which will execute the given function. Returns zero on success, or nonzero on error.
void fiberYield();
Yield execution control to another fiber. This simply calls sched_yield in the kernel thread implementation.
void waitForAllFibers();
Waits for all the fibers to exit, and frees resources associated with each one. If called from a child fiber in the user space implementations, it will return once all other fibers have exited. If called from a child fiber in the kernel implementation, it will return immediately. Returns zero on success, or nonzero on error.

Figure 2 shows the main function from the sample application included with the library. It creates three fibers executing different functions, waits until they have all completed, then returns.

 1 int main()
 2 {
 3   // Initialize the fiber library
 4   initFibers();
 5  
 6   // Go fibers!
 7   spawnFiber( &fiber1 );
 8   spawnFiber( &fibonacchi );
 9   spawnFiber( &squares );
10 
11   // Since these are not preemptive, we must allow them to run
12   waitForAllFibers();
13  
14   // The program quits
15   return 0;
16 }

Figure 2: Example program using the fiber library

Implementing Kernel Threads on Linux

Linux takes a unique approach to threads. On Linux, threads and processes are treated the same. They are both considered to be tasks. The difference is that threads share the same memory space, file mappings and (in general) signal handlers. There is an excellent post from Linus Torvalds to the Linux Kernel Mailing List that explains the advantages of this implementation . This means that in the process list in Figure 1 , the processes may actually be threads. For example, the four mozilla-bin processes are actually threads inside a single process.

Linux使用一個特殊的方法實現線程。在Linux上，進程和線程在本質上是一樣的，它們都被認為是任務。唯一的區別是現成共享內存空間，文件描述符和信號處理程序(通常情況下)。在Linux Kernel Mailing List上，Linus Torvalds發過一個經典的帖子來闡述這種實現方式的優點。 在Linux上，內核線程可以通過系統調用clone來創建。這個系統調用跟fork相似，都是創建一個任務。只不過clone可以指定共享哪些資源。在創建線程時，我們可以共享儘可能多的資源：內存空間，文件描述符和信號處理函數。當線程退出，發出SIGCHLD信號時，wait將會返回。 第一個挑戰是為線程分配棧空間。在libfier中使用的是最簡單的方法，即使用malloc在堆中分配棧空間。這意味著必須要估計一個棧的最大值。如果棧在使用時超出了最大值，會引起內存衝突。在bb_threads中，是使用mprotect在棧底創建一個barrier，這樣在棧溢出的時候會引發段錯誤。最好的方法是Linux pthreads的實現，是使用mmap來分配內存，這樣的話，內存隨需隨分配，如果系統不能分配另外的內存，將會產生segmentation violation。 傳遞給clone的棧指針必須指向棧頂，因為在多數處理器中，棧是向下生長的。為了避免內存洩露，線程退出時必須釋放棧空間。Libfiber庫使用wait等待線程退出，然後使用free釋放棧空間。圖3顯示了創建線程的例子。請通過libfiber-clone.c查看完整的實現。如果想瞭解Linux pthread如何實現創建線程，請看 "The Fibers of Threads"。

On Linux, kernel threads are created with the clone system call. This system call is similar to fork in that it creates a task which is executing the current program. However it differs in that clone specifies which resources should be shared. To create a thread, we call clone to create a task which shares as much as possible: The memory space, file descriptors and signal handlers. The signal to be sent when the thread exists is SIGCHLD so wait will return when a thread exits.

The first challenge is allocating a stack for the thread. The simplest solution, used in libfiber, is allocating the stack on the heap using malloc . This means that an estimate of the maximum stack size must be made. If the stack grows larger, memory corruption will occur. A solution used by bb_threads , is to create a barrier at the bottom of the stack with mprotect . This way, the thread will cause a segmentation fault when it overflows the stack. The best solution, used by the Linux pthreads implementation, is to use mmap to allocate memory, with flags specifying a region of memory which is allocated as it is used. This way, memory is allocated for the stack as it is needed, and a segmentation violation will occur if the system is unable to allocate additional memory.

The stack pointer passed to clone must reference the top of the chunk of memory, since on most processors the stack grows down. This is done by adding the size of the region to the pointer returned by malloc . To avoid a memory leak, the stack must be freed once the thread has exited. The libfiber library waits for threads to exit using wait , then frees the stack using free . Figure 3 shows an example of creating a thread. See libfiber-clone.c in the libfiber package for the full implementation. For details about how Linux's pthread implementation creates threads, see "The Fibers of Threads " from Linux Magazine.

#include <malloc.h>
#include <sys/types.h>
#include <sys/wait.h>
#include <signal.h>
#include <sched.h>
#include <stdio.h>

// 64kB stack
#define FIBER_STACK 1024*64

// The child thread will execute this function
int threadFunction( void* argument )
{
printf( "child thread exiting\n" );
return 0;
}

int main()
{
void* stack;
pid_t pid;

// Allocate the stack
stack = malloc( FIBER_STACK );
if ( stack == 0 )
{
perror( "malloc: could not allocate stack" );
exit( 1 );
}

printf( "Creating child thread\n" );

// Call the clone system call to create the child thread
pid = clone( &threadFunction, (char*) stack + FIBER_STACK,
SIGCHLD | CLONE_FS | CLONE_FILES | CLONE_SIGHAND | CLONE_VM, 0 );
if ( pid == -1 )
{
perror( "clone" );
exit( 2 );
}

// Wait for the child thread to exit
pid = waitpid( pid, 0, 0 );
if ( pid == -1 )
{
perror( "waitpid" );
exit( 3 );
}

// Free the stack
free( stack );

printf( "Child thread returned and stack freed.\n" );

return 0;
}

Figure 3: Simple clone Thread Example

Implementing Fibers Using makecontext

Modern Unix systems include library functions for manipulating the execution context, contained in ucontext.h . These functions are getcontext , setcontext , swapcontext and makecontext . Essentially, getcontext saves the current execution context, setcontext switches to the specified execution context, swapcontext will save the current context and switch to another and makecontext creates a new execution context. To create a new fiber, we call getcontext to retrieve the current context then modify the members of the ucontext_t struct to specify the new context. Again, we must allocate a new stack, but this time the library takes care of the direction of the stack growth. Then we call makecontext and specify the function and arguments to execute in the fiber.

The remaining challenge is that in this implementation, the fibers must explicitly yield control to allow other fibers to run. The swapcontext function can be used to stop executing one fiber and continue executing another. Figure 4 shows a simple program which creates a child fiber and switches between the child and the parent. See libfiber-uc.c in the libfiber package for the full implementation.

#include <malloc.h>
#include <ucontext.h>
#include <stdio.h>

// 64kB stack
#define FIBER_STACK 1024*64

ucontext_t child, parent;

// The child thread will execute this function
void threadFunction()
{
printf( "Child fiber yielding to parent" );
swapcontext( &child, &parent );
printf( "Child thread exiting\n" );
swapcontext( &child, &parent );
}

int main()
{
// Get the current execution context
getcontext( &child );

// Modify the context to a new stack
child.uc_link = 0;
child.uc_stack.ss_sp = malloc( FIBER_STACK );
child.uc_stack.ss_size = FIBER_STACK;
child.uc_stack.ss_flags = 0;
if ( child.uc_stack.ss_sp == 0 )
{
perror( "malloc: Could not allocate stack" );
exit( 1 );
}

// Create the new context
printf( "Creating child fiber\n" );
makecontext( &child, &threadFunction, 0 );

// Execute the child context
printf( "Switching to child fiber\n" );
swapcontext( &parent, &child );
printf( "Switching to child fiber again\n" );
swapcontext( &parent, &child );

// Free the stack
free( child.uc_stack.ss_sp );

printf( "Child fiber returned and stack freed\n" );

return 0;
}

Figure 4: Simple makecontext Fiber Example

Implementing Fibers Using longjmp

ANSI C provides functions for saving and restoring the execution context for graceful error handling. setjmp saves the current execution context, and longjmp returns to a previously saved context. The one new challenge to implementing fibers with these functions is that they do not provide a way to create a new stack. They simply restore a previous stack frame. To create the stack, we use sigaltstack to allocate an alternate stack for the signal handler, set up a signal handler, then call it on the new stack using raise . The signal handler saves its current state hen returns to get rid of the "signal handler context". Finally, the fiber is ready to run. Figure 5 shows a minimal program that uses this technique to set up an alternate stack. See libfiber-clone.c in the libfiber package for the full implementation. This technique is used by GNU Pth to implement fibers in a very portable fashion.

 1 #include <malloc.h>
 2 #include <setjmp.h>
 3 #include <signal.h>
 4 #include <stdio.h>
 5 
 6 // 64kB stack
 7 #define FIBER_STACK 1024*64
 8 
 9 jmp_buf child, parent;
10 
11 // The child thread will execute this function
12 void threadFunction()
13 {
14   printf( "Child fiber yielding to parent\n" );
15   if ( setjmp( child ) )
16   {
17     printf( "Child thread exiting\n" );
18     longjmp( parent, 1 );
19   }
20 
21   longjmp( parent, 1 );
22 }
23 
24 void signalHandler( int arg )
25 {
26   if ( setjmp( child ) )
27   {
28     threadFunction();
29   }
30  
31   return;
32 }
33 
34 int main()
35 {
36   stack_t stack;
37   struct sigaction sa;
38  
39   // Create the new stack
40   stack.ss_flags = 0;
41   stack.ss_size = FIBER_STACK;
42   stack.ss_sp = malloc( FIBER_STACK );
43   if ( stack.ss_sp == 0 )
44   {
45     perror( "malloc: Could not allocate stack." );
46     exit( 1 );
47   }
48   sigaltstack( &stack, 0 );
49  
50   // Set up the custom signal handler
51   sa.sa_handler = &signalHandler;
52   sa.sa_flags = SA_ONSTACK;
53   sigemptyset( &sa.sa_mask );
54   sigaction( SIGUSR1, &sa, 0 );
55  
56   // Send the signal to call the function on the new stack
57   printf( "Creating child fiber\n" );
58   raise( SIGUSR1 );
59  
60   // Execute the child context
61   printf( "Switching to child fiber\n" );
62   if ( setjmp( parent ) )
63   {
64     printf( "Switching to child fiber again\n" );
65     if ( setjmp( parent ) == 0 ) longjmp( child, 1 );
66   }
67   else longjmp( child, 1 );
68  
69   // Free the stack
70   free( stack.ss_sp );
71   printf( "Child fiber returned and stack freed\n" );
72   return 0;
73 }

Figure 5: Simple longjmp Fiber Example

Conclusion

The implementation of libfiber can be examined to understand how threads and fibers are created by libraries which provide them. This can be useful when analyzing the performance impact of various multiprocessing techniques. The library was developed and tested on Linux, however, the fiber implementations should be portable across most Unix platforms. The thread implementation, on the other hand, is Linux specific, due to the clone system call.

實現一個簡單的線程庫libfiber可以讓我們更好的理解線程庫是如何實現線程的，當我們在分析不同多線程工具的時候，上面的這些經驗就會派上用場。本線程庫是在Linux開發並測試的，但是真正的線程庫應該是可以移植到Unix平台上的，從這點上來說，本線程庫實現的內核線程是Linux專有的，因為它是利用clone系統調用來實現的。

Resources

Pthreads Tutorial Part 1 , Part 2 , Part 3 - How to use the pthreads library
LinuxThreads FAQ - Frequently asked questions about Linux's pthread implementation
The Fibers of Threads - An article explaining how Linux's pthread library is implemented
Bare-bones threads [local mirror ] - A simple Linux thread library that uses clone and provides mutexes
GNU Portable Threads (Pth) - User space thread library for nearly any platform imaginable
Portable Multithreading - A excellent paper describing how to create user space threads
Linux Kernel Mailing List - The definitive resource for Linux operating system discussions, and development.
Kernel Traffic - A summary of the activity on the Linux Kernel Mailing List
JAWS: Understanding High Performance Web Systems - The performance implications of processes, threads and fibers
Cooperative Task Management - A 2002 USENIX paper from Microsoft that describes the software engineering advantages and disadvantages of different concurrency models in great detail.

Comments

The following are responses to questions about this document, some of which resulted in some changes.

2002-10-21: Re: About locking in multi-threaded environments 2002-10-21: Re: thread library [passing multiple parameters to new threads]

Revision History

2003-12-10 : Whoops. Fixed another IBM thread link.
2003-02-20 : IBM's Posix Threads tutorial has moved. I've also linked to all three parts.
2002-10-24 : Clarified the language in the section discussing the need for locks with user space threads. Concurrency errors can occur with user space threads. However, code between two calls to yield() (or functions that in turn call yield) will always execute atomically from the perspective of the program. One sentence was modified to use softer language as follows: This means that many some of the locks required for threads are not may not be needed. A reference was added to the Microsoft Research paper on Cooperative Task Management , which has a good quote on this subject and is a good paper on this subject in general.
2002-10-24 : Added a comments section with responses to questions about this document.

在Linux上實現線程庫-紅聯Linux系統門戶

原文：Implementing a Thread Library on Linux
作者：Evan Jones
翻譯：楊碩

在程序在運行的時候，通常都是只有一條主線的，有些時候，這是效率不高的。有很多程序必須要能同時做很多工作。比如說，GUI程序必須在處理程序邏輯的同時重畫界面，響應用戶輸入。Web服務器必須同時向成百上千的客戶發送信息。線程可以解決這些難題。所有的現代操作系統都提供線程庫，比如標準Posix線程。特別是，我對線程的工作原理十分好奇，所以在學習了一些C和Linux內核的知識後，我開始建立自己的線程庫。
多任務
在傳統的操作系統中，提供了實現多任務的兩種工具，一種是進程，一種是線程。
進程
每個程序都是獨立的進程。操作系統在所有進程間分配資源，並且為了防止一個進程修改其他進程的資源，進程間是彼此完全獨立的。但是，多個進程配合完成一項任務也是很常見的。比如說，圖1展示了我的Linux系統下同時進行的進程，其中有4個進程執行mozilla-bin。在這種情況下，進程間需要相互通信，因此操作系統提供了進程間通信(IPC)的工具，比如有信號，共享內存和管道。
Process ID Command
1 init
142 /sbin/syslogd
183 /usr/bin/X11/X
266 esd
270 sawfish
275 panel
277 gmc
279 gnome-terminal
291 bash
319 /usr/bin/mozilla-bin
341 /usr/bin/scite
344 /usr/bin/mozilla-bin
345 /usr/bin/mozilla-bin
346 /usr/bin/mozilla-bin
2568 ps
圖1 Linux系統上的進程列表

線程
進程間通信是非常簡單和便於使用的，但是，如果有很多進程需要共享彼此的資源，模型就會變得十分複雜。線程提供了一種解決這類問題的簡單和高效的方法。一個進程可以含有多個線程，除了環境上下文(堆棧和CPU寄存器)以外，所有的資源在線程間都是共享的。因此，如果一個線程修改了某個共享資源，則這種改變對於其它線程也是可見的。線程的缺點就是引入了一個新問題，即要避免兩個線程同時訪問某一個共享資源。
內核線程
現代操作系統在內核級上支持線程。這意味著線程直接由操作系統的調度器進行調度，這可以帶來大幅度的性能提升。內核線程的缺點是線程切換的花銷比較大，因此並發多個線程可能比單線程的效率要低，因為線程切換佔用了一定的時間。這也是單線程服務器，如thttpd，要比多線程服務器，如Apache性能好的原因。JAWS research project對用不同多任務方法實現的web服務器的性能作了很深入的分析。
用戶線程
線程也可以在用戶級上實現，這意味著進行線程調度是由程序自身或線程庫來完成的。如果線程在用戶級上實現，同樣也會有很大的線程切換開銷，但是，這種開銷要比在內核級的線程切換小很多。有些時候，用戶線程被稱為fiber(纖程)，暗示著它要比內核線程「輕」。一個簡單的線程庫
為了完全玩轉這些概念，libfiber誕生了。它實現了用戶線程和內核線程。該線程庫僅僅實現了線程的創建，銷毀及調度。它只能被用作教學，因為還有很多信號和同步的問題沒有解決。在編寫真實的程序時，可以使用內核線程庫pthreads或用戶線程庫GNU Portable Threads (Pth)。
Libfiber 接口
void initFibers();
初始化線程庫的內部數據結構。必須在使用其他函數前調用。
int spawnFiber( void (*func)(void) );
創建線程，該線程將會執行給定的函數。成功返回零，錯誤返回非零。
void fiberYield();
主動放棄CPU。在內核線程實現中，只是簡單的調用sched_yield。
void waitForAllFibers();
等待所有線程退出，釋放資源。如果在用戶線程中調用，只有所有其它線程全部返回該函數才會返回；如果在內核線程中調用，它會立即返回。成功返回零，錯誤返回非零。

圖2顯示的是用該線程庫編寫的樣例程序。它創建了三個線程，分別執行不同的函數，等待所有線程退出後返回。

int main()
{
// Initialize the fiber library
initFibers();

// Go fibers!
spawnFiber( &fiber1 );
spawnFiber( &fibonacchi );
spawnFiber( &squares );

// Since these are not preemptive, we must allow them to run
waitForAllFibers();

// The program quits
return 0;
}

圖2 使用線程庫的樣例程序

在Linux上實現內核線程
Linux使用一個特殊的方法實現線程。在Linux上，進程和線程在本質上是一樣的，它們都被認為是任務。唯一的區別是現成共享內存空間，文件描述符和信號處理程序(通常情況下)。在Linux Kernel Mailing List上，Linus Torvalds發過一個經典的帖子來闡述這種實現方式的優點。
在Linux上，內核線程可以通過系統調用clone來創建。這個系統調用跟fork相似，都是創建一個任務。只不過clone可以指定共享哪些資源。在創建線程時，我們可以共享儘可能多的資源：內存空間，文件描述符和信號處理函數。當線程退出，發出SIGCHLD信號時，wait將會返回。
第一個挑戰是為線程分配棧空間。在libfier中使用的是最簡單的方法，即使用malloc在堆中分配棧空間。這意味著必須要估計一個棧的最大值。如果棧在使用時超出了最大值，會引起內存衝突。在bb_threads中，是使用mprotect在棧底創建一個barrier，這樣在棧溢出的時候會引發段錯誤。最好的方法是Linux pthreads的實現，是使用mmap來分配內存，這樣的話，內存隨需隨分配，如果系統不能分配另外的內存，將會產生segmentation violation。
傳遞給clone的棧指針必須指向棧頂，因為在多數處理器中，棧是向下生長的。為了避免內存洩露，線程退出時必須釋放棧空間。Libfiber庫使用wait等待線程退出，然後使用free釋放棧空間。圖3顯示了創建線程的例子。請通過libfiber-clone.c查看完整的實現。如果想瞭解Linux pthread如何實現創建線程，請看"The Fibers of Threads"。
#include
#include
#include
#include
#include
#include

// 64kB stack
#define FIBER_STACK 1024*64

// The child thread will execute this function
int threadFunction( void* argument )
{
printf( "child thread exiting\n" );
return 0;
}

int main()
{
void* stack;
pid_t pid;

// Allocate the stack
stack = malloc( FIBER_STACK );
if ( stack == 0 )
{
perror( "malloc: could not allocate stack" );
exit( 1 );
}

printf( "Creating child thread\n" );

// Call the clone system call to create the child thread
pid = clone( &threadFunction, (char*) stack + FIBER_STACK,
SIGCHLD | CLONE_FS | CLONE_FILES | CLONE_SIGHAND | CLONE_VM, 0 );
if ( pid == -1 )
{
perror( "clone" );
exit( 2 );
}

// Wait for the child thread to exit
pid = waitpid( pid, 0, 0 );
if ( pid == -1 )
{
perror( "waitpid" );
exit( 3 );
}

// Free the stack
free( stack );

printf( "Child thread returned and stack freed.\n" );

return 0;
}

圖3 用clone實現線程

使用makecontext實現用戶線程
現代Unix系統都在ucontext.h中提供用於上下文切換的函數，這些函數有getcontext, setcontext，swapcontext 和makecontext。其中，getcontext用於保存當前上下文，setcontext用於切換上下文，swapcontext會保存當前上下文並切換到另一個上下文，makecontext創建一個新的上下文。實現用戶線程的過程是：我們首先調用getcontext獲得當前上下文，然後修改ucontext_t指定新的上下文。同樣的，我們需要開闢棧空間，但是這次實現的線程庫要涉及棧生長的方向。然後我們調用makecontext切換上下文，並指定用戶線程中要執行的函數。
在這種實現中還有一個挑戰，即一個線程必須可以主動讓出CPU給其它線程。swapcontext函數可以完成這個任務，圖4展示了一個這種實現的樣例程序，child線程和parent線程不斷切換以達到多線程的效果。在libfiber-uc.c文件中可以看到完整的實現。
#include
#include
#include

// 64kB stack
#define FIBER_STACK 1024*64

ucontext_t child, parent;

// The child thread will execute this function
void threadFunction()
{
printf( "Child fiber yielding to parent" );
swapcontext( &child, &parent );
printf( "Child thread exiting\n" );
swapcontext( &child, &parent );
}

int main()
{
// Get the current execution context
getcontext( &child );

// Modify the context to a new stack
child.uc_link = 0;
child.uc_stack.ss_sp = malloc( FIBER_STACK );
child.uc_stack.ss_size = FIBER_STACK;
child.uc_stack.ss_flags = 0;
if ( child.uc_stack.ss_sp == 0 )
{
perror( "malloc: Could not allocate stack" );
exit( 1 );
}

// Create the new context
printf( "Creating child fiber\n" );
makecontext( &child, &threadFunction, 0 );

// Execute the child context
printf( "Switching to child fiber\n" );
swapcontext( &parent, &child );
printf( "Switching to child fiber again\n" );
swapcontext( &parent, &child );

// Free the stack
free( child.uc_stack.ss_sp );

printf( "Child fiber returned and stack freed\n" );

return 0;
}
圖4用makecontext實現線程

結論
實現一個簡單的線程庫libfiber可以讓我們更好的理解線程庫是如何實現線程的，當我們在分析不同多線程工具的時候，上面的這些經驗就會派上用場。本線程庫是在Linux開發並測試的，但是真正的線程庫應該是可以移植到Unix平台上的，從這點上來說，本線程庫實現的內核線程是Linux專有的，因為它是利用clone系統調用來實現的。